DERIK SCHAEFER

1932 Pelorus Ave, Seal Beach, CA 90740 ◆ (702) 373-3099 ◆ Derik.P.Schaefer@gmail.com

Professional Summary

Accomplished U.S. Coast Guard service member with eleven years of experience managing law enforcement and search and rescue teams; including over four years of experience conducting counter-trafficking and coastal security operations at sea. I am a reputable leader with several years of experience directly supervising and managing junior personnel.

WORK HISTORY

United States Coast Guard (USCG), Active Duty, 2009 to Current Operations Specialist First Class (Rank OS1 / Pay Grade E-6)

Awards: Coast Guard Achievement Medal, Commandant's Letter of Commendation (2), Coast Guard Unit Commendation Ribbon, Coast Guard Meritorious Unit Commendation Ribbon (4), Coast Guard Good Conduct Medal (3), National Defense Service Medal, Global War on Terror Service Medal, Coast Guard Special Operations Service Ribbon (2), Coast Guard Sea Service Ribbon (2), Coast Guard Pistol Marksman Ribbon

Search and Rescue Controller & Situation Unit Watchstander, 2018 to Current Sector Los Angeles Long Beach – San Pedro, CA

- Evaluate reports of distress and execute critical, time sensitive decisions based on limited or uncertain information
- Plan and prioritize response actions for maritime emergencies utilizing aircraft, surface vessels, and other government agencies
- Manage field teams conducting maritime security, safety, and marine environmental protection missions
- Author and verify case reports and chronologies for records keeping

Operations Specialist in Charge, 2017 to 2018

USCGC STEADFAST – Warrenton, OR

- Critical member in the interdiction of over 30,000 pounds of cocaine worth more than \$500 million
- Senior enlisted person in the Operations Department. Key operational decision maker on the Cutter. Frequently acted as a liaison between STEADFAST and other CG & DoD units
- Managed a five person OS shop and 12 person CIC watch team
- Created a training & professional development program for junior personnel
- COMSEC inventory manager; properly maintained all classified material for STEADFAST. Handled all EKMS records, reports, audits, key issues & destruction. Provided weekly training to all EKMS users
- Responsible for all physical and personnel security matters onboard STEADFAST

Situation Unit & Communications Unit Watchstander, 2013 to 2017 Sector Puget Sound Command Center – Seattle, WA

- Integral to the successful completion of 383 pollution incidents, 293 marine safety incidents, 127 law enforcement cases, and 315 search and rescue cases
- Tracked and monitored the status of all planned or emergent operations within the Sector's Area of Responsibility. Managed field teams conducting maritime security, safety, and environmental protection missions
- COMSEC inventory manager; properly maintained all classified material. Handled all EKMS records, reports, audits, key issues & destruction. Provided weekly training to all EKMS users. Responsible for the issue and destruction of keying material for outlying Sector Units
- Monitored maritime distress frequencies. Obtained vital information from persons in distress

Combat Information Center Watch Supervisor, 2010 to 2013

USCGC NORTHLAND – Portsmouth, VA

- Key member in the interdiction of over 3,500 pounds of cocaine worth over \$42 million
- Adapted tactical plans in response to information from overhead surveillance, intelligence sources, and secure information feeds resulted in the apprehension of Drug Trafficking Organization (DTO) equipment and personnel
- Subject matter expert on the drafting, handling and dissemination of unclassified and classified messages
- Responsible for creating and maintaining complex satellite communications circuits

EDUCATION —
Bachelor of Science in Business: Business Administration, 2016
Southern New Hampshire University - Hooksett, NH
Community Involvement

- USCG Rep for a Special Olympics of Southern California fundraising event; over \$190,000 raised
- Volunteer with multiple animal welfare non-profits in the Southern California area
- Northwest Harvest volunteer. Distributed over 40,000 pounds of food; provided 39,025 meals to food banks, meal programs, and high-need schools
- Presented information on CG search and rescue to over 350 students as part of the BASE LALB 2019
 "Day of Discovery" event